Finding Aid for the Japanese American Research Project Collection about Japanese in the U.S. (Yuji Ichioka papers) LSC.2010.00
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Materials regarding the Japanese consulates in the United States, 33 linear feet
  The Japanese American Research Project (JARP) also acquired on microfilm the Collection of papers from the Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs dealing with Japanese emigration into the United States and other countries (ryji Hkoku [characters] [consular report]) regarding overseas migration and emigration from Japan, the Japanese in the United States, and anti-Japanese activities in the continental United States which are preserved in the Gaimusho Gaik Shirykan [characters] in Tokyo. As these materials are not part of the JARP collation (No. 2010) housed in the Special Collections Department of UCLA's University Research Library, they are not listed in this check list. Those who want to use the materials should consult A Buried Past: An Annotated Bibliography of the Japanese American Research Project Collection (Berkeley: University of California Press, 1974),pp. 19- 34. Cecil H. Uyehara, A Checklist of Archives in the Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs, Tokyo, Japan, 1868-1945 (Washington, D.C.: U.S. Congress, 1954) lists the Gaimusho archival materials regarding Japanese immigrants in the United States and their immigration into America, which are held in the Library of Congress on microfilm. Selected ryji hkoku regarding Japanese immigrants and anti-Japanese activities in the United States are also included in Gaimusho, Nihon Gaik Bunsho [characters], but these documents are reprinted without exhibits--for example, newspaper clippings, reports prepared by the Japanese Association of America, and other documents which are no longer available in America.
  - Records and documents regarding the Japanese Consulate of Los Angeles., 32.0 linear ft.
    - Trokusha kdo [characters] [Registrants' cards]., Approximately 51,000 5 × 8 index cards (Box 164-225)
      Trokusha kdo [characters] [Registrants' cards]. 5 × 8 index cards, each of which contains various items of information on a Japanese male and his family members, residing within the jurisdiction of the Japanese Consulate of Los Angeles (Counties of Imperial, Los Angeles, Orange, Riverside, San Bernardino, San Diego, San Luis Obispo, Santa Barbara, and Ventura in the state of California; and the states of Arizona and New Mexico), who completed the required registration at the Consulate.
      Initially, these cards were prepared to serve as the data base for the issuance of various certificates required by Japanese government laws and regulations and the United States Immigration Law, as well as for the purpose of compiling census or other statistical reports. The cards are grouped into three major sets. The first set contains over 42,000 cards of the households who completed the registration between 1920 and 1924; the second includes 8,333 individuals and families who registered during the period from 1925 to 1940; and the third 82 cards of those Japanese who registered in the year 1941.
      Entries on each card include: names and place of birth, social status (shizoku [characters] or heimin [characters]), marital status, profession or occupation, names and ages of family members, their relationships to the household-head (kach [characters]), the date of arrival and the port of original entry, property holdings (if farming, whether or not the family owned land and how many acres they were farming), and current address. In each group, cards are filed in an alphabetical order by the surnames of household heads.
    - Trokusha meibo [characters] [Roster of registrants]., (4 volumes) (Box 226-227)
      A comprehensive registry of the heads and members of Japanese households who established their residency in the areas under the jurisdiction of the Japanese Consulate of Los Angeles as of December 31, 1925. In the previous year, the 1924 Immigration Law was enacted and the immigration of Japanese into the United States was completely stopped. This registry was probably compiled to find out how many Japanese had remained in the United States as residents, who they were, and what their occupation or jobs were.
    - Zairy shmei hakk kiroku [characters] [Register book for the issuance the Certificate of Residence by the Consulate]., December 1920-October 1941; (1 volume) (Box 228)
    - Zaigai homp jitsugy dantai shirabe [characters] [Survey report on economic organizations established by overseas Japanese]., March 1939; (1 binder) (Box 228)
      A list of Japanese commercial, business, and agricultural associations organized or established in Southern California, compiled in March 1939.
    - Centennial Award list., 1960; 1 folder (Box 228)
      A list of those Japanese Americans (Issei and Nisei) who were awarded a medal or commendation by the Japanese government in 1960, in commemoration of the 100th anniversary of the ratification of the Japan-United States Treaty of Commerce and Amity of 1858. List only includes those individuals who resided within the jurisdiction of the Japanese Consulate of Los Angeles. Compiled in 1960.
  - Documents regarding the Japanese Consulate of San Francisco, 0.5 linear ft.
    - Ksakubutsu narabini eiks [characters] [Crops and acreage: A survey report]., 1922-1923; (1 item) (Box 228)
      The report is for those Japanese who farmed in Stanislaus and Merced Counties in California in the years 1922- 1923. It shows the types of crops they grew, and how many acres of land they farmed (owned or leased). Compiled by the Japanese Consulate of San Francisco.
    - Jitsuj chsa [characters] [Fact-finding survey: A report]., 1926; (1 item) (Box 228)
      A statistical report on the Japanese residing in Stanislaus and Merced Counties in California. Compiled by the Japanese Consulate of San Francisco.
  - Documents regarding the Japanese Consulate of Seattle., 0.5 linear ft.
    - Shak Nihon Ryjikan, comp. Shichi-gatsu tsuitachi yori jisshi saretaru shin-Imin-H to chi jik [characters] [The new Immigration Law and its provisions to which one should pay attention]., 1924; 32pp., 1 item) (Box 228)
      An information booklet to explain the new provisions of the 1924 Immigration Act, and what impact the passage of this new Immigration Law had on the future of the Japanese immigration to the United States. Prepared and distributed by the Japanese Consulate of Seattle.
    - Dai-yonkai Kokusei Chsahy [characters] [The Fourth National Census]., September 1, 1935; 1 volume. (Box 228)
      A report prepared by the Japanese Consulate of Seattle for those Japanese residing within the jurisdiction of the Japanese Consulate of Seattle for the Fourth National Census of Japan.
    - Nichi-Bei shk hyaku-nen kinen hyshsha risuto [characters] [Recipients of commendations from the Japanese government in commemoration of the 100th anniversary of Japan-United States amity: A list]. Compiled by the Japanese Consulate of Seattle., [1960]; 1 folder. (Box 228)
  - Japanese consulates documents (Photocopies), 0.5 linear ft.
    - Nichi-Bei shk hyaku-nen kinen Gaimu Daijin hi-hyshsha risuto [characters] [Recipients of commendations from the Minister for Foreign Affairs of Japan in commemoration of the 100th anniversary of Japan-United States amity: A list]., [1960]; (1 item)
      Lists compiled separately by the Japanese Consulates of Honolulu, Houston, New York, Portland, and San Francisco.
  - Records regarding the Gamush [Japanese Ministry of Foreign Affairs] (Box 228)
    - Jokunsha meibo [characters] [Roster of those individuals who were awarded a medal]., 1 folder. (Box 228)
      A list of Issei, Nisei, and other Americans who were awarded a medal by the Japanese government between 1947 and 1968.
    - Gaimusho, Amerika-kyoku [characters] [North America Bureau], Nichi-Bei shk tssh hyaku-nen kinen Gaimu Daijin hyshsha meibo [characters]., 1960; (1 item) (Box 228)
      [Recipients of the Foreign Minister's commendations in commemoration of the 100th anniversary of Japan-United States commerce: A list].
    - Photograph of dinner in honor of K. Hori, Consul of Japan., 1934 (Box 864)
- Organizational Materials
  - Japanese American Citizens League (JACL), 8.5 linear ft.
    - Materials regarding the National Headquarters of JACL
      - Official minutes of the Biennial National JACL Conventions.., 1930; 1946-1960; (11 items) (Box 296)
        The First Convention (1930)
        Emergency National Conference (1942)
        The Ninth to Sixteenth Conventions (1946-1960)
      - National Convention souvenir booklets. The Sixteenth to Nineteenth., 1960-1966; (3 folders) (Box 297)
      - Official minutes of the National Council meetings. The Seventeenth to Nineteenth., 1962-1964; (3 folders) (Box 297)
      - JACL membership bulletin., April 1947-August 1954; (14 issues) (Box 297)
      - Supporting Membership plan, 1953 (Box 302, Folder 4)
      - Reports prepared for the JACL National Headquarters. (Box 301)
        - JACL Washington Office, Returning World War II sequestrated private property: JACL statement to the Subcommittee on Commerce and Finance, Committee on Interstate and Foreign Commerce, House of Representatives., 1961; (1 item) (Box 301)
        - Mike Masaoka, Final Report., 1944; (1 item) (Box 301)
        - Mike Masaoka, To eliminate racial discrimination in immigration: The Administration's Immigration Bill S. 500, H.R. 2580., 1965; (1 item) (Box 301)
        - Mike Masaoka, Report of Washington JACL representatives, 1962-1964 biennium to 18th Biennial National Convention of Japanese American Citizens League., January 29, 1964; (1 item) (Box 301)
        - Masaoka-Ishikawa and Associates, Washington Report., August 8, 1961 and January 13, 1964; (2 items) (Box 301)
        - Office of Fact and Figures, The Japanese Problem: The answer to a series of questions asked of a nation-wide cross-section of 3,471 adult persons., April 21, 1942; (1 item) (Box 301)
        - Questionnaire "Survey: Japanese in Farming.", 1948 (Box 302, Folder 5)
      - Printed Materials. (Box 297)
        - Box score on legislation affecting persons of Japanese ancestry in the first session... 80th Congress. San Francisco: Japanese American Citizens League Anti-Discrimination Committee, Inc., 1947; (1 item) (Box 297)
        - For better Americans in a greater America: The story of the Japanese American Citizens League., n.d. (1951?); (1 item) (Box 297)
        - The J.A.C.L. occupation survey of the Japanese communities in the greater Pacific Northeast district. National JACL Committee on Equal Employment Opportunity., 1965; (1 item) (Box 297)
        - Silence is consent., n.d.; (1 item) (Box 297)
        - Togasaki, T. A good conscience: An address at the pioneer night of the Japanese American Citizens League, at its convention in September of 1934., n.d.; (1 item) (Box 297)
        - Pacific Citizen correspondence, 1953-1956 (Box 302, Folder 6)
      - Printed reports and clippings of magazine and newspaper articles filed at the JACL National Headquarters., 1936-1949 (Box 298-300)
    - Materials regarding District Councils, Local Chapters and Affiliated Organizations
      - Materials regarding district councils. (Box 297,301,303)
        - Eighth Biennial Pacific Southwest District Council Convention program. West Los Angeles Chapter, Los Angeles., May 1963; (1 item) (Box 297)
        - Fifteenth Biennial Pacific Northwest District Council Convention program. Gresham Troutdale Chapter, Gresham, Oregon., December 1967; (1 item) (Box 297)
        - Intermountain District Council Fourteenth Biennial Convention program. Salt Lake City Chapter, Salt Lake City, Utah., December 1964; (1 item) (Box 297)
        - JACL Anti-Axis Committee of the Southern District Council, Minutes of the Anti-Axis Committee meetings., December 8-27, 1941; (1 item) (Box 301)
        - JACL Fourth Biennial Eastern District Council-Midwest District Council Convention program. Twin Cities Chapter, Minneapolis, Minnesota., May 1961; (1 item) (Box 297)
        - Minutes. Intermountain District Council meetings. Salt Lake City, Utah., December 1941-August 1955; (14 items) (Box 303)
        - Tenth Annual chapter clinic program. Pacific Southwest District Council. Los Angeles., February 1963; (1 item) (Box 297)
    - Documents and records regarding the Pocatello Chapter, JACL. Pocatello, Idaho., 5.0 linear ft. (Box 304-311, Box 724)
      - Articles of Incorporation of JACL Pocatello Chapter., October 1, 1954; (1 item) (Box 306)
      - Bills and receipts., 1940-1953 (Box 304)
      - Constitution, JACL Pocatello Chapter., n.d.; (1 item) (Box 306)
      - Correspondence., June 1941-November 1958; (122 items) (Box 306)
      - Correspondence regarding the National JACL Endowment Fund., January 1953-February 1954; (4 items) (Box 306)
      - Correspondence regarding the JACL National Headquarters., October 1941-Ocrtober 1958; (63 items) (Box 306)
      - Correspondence and financial reports regarding the National JACL Credit Union., December 1955-January 1958; (8 items) (Box 306)
      - Financial records and account books., 1941-1958 (Box 307-311, Box 724)
      - Membership fees and donations: receipts., 1940-1953 (Box 305)
      - Membership roster., 1967; (1 item) (Box 305)
      - Membership records., 1956-1957; (133 cards) (Box 305)
      - Minutes. Intermountain District Council meeting., March 20, 1955; (1 item) (Box 306)
      - National legislative materials., January 1947-August 1956; (101 items) (Box 311)
      - Papers regarding sugar beet contracts., March 1950-October 1957; (7 items) (Box 306)
      - Report, JACL Anti-Discrimination Committee., May 11, 1950; (2 items) (Box 306)
      - Miscellaneous materials., 1941-1958 (Box 306)
    - Records regarding other JACL chapters, 1.5 linear ft.
      - Boise Valley Chapter, Idaho. Boise Valley J.A.C.L. census report., 1963; (1 item) (Box 303)
      - Issei Story questionnaires completed by the Issei residing in: Salt Lake City, Utah; San Luis Obispo, California; and Southern California., (Approximately 160 items) (Box 303)
      - Miscellaneous papers regarding the Seabrook Chapter, New Jersey., 1958-1960; (3 items) (Box 303)
      - The 35th anniversary and testimonial dinner honoring Saburo Kido. Downtown Los Angeles Chapter., July 25, 1964; (1 item) (Box 297)
      - The 20th anniversary (1947-1967) souvenir booklet. Omaha Chapter, Nebraska., (1 item) (Box 297)
      - M.I.S. 25th Anniversary Reunion Committee, Military Intelligence Service Language School, 25th anniversary reunion program. San Francisco., 1966; (1 item) (Box 297)
      - Minutes of the Intermountain District Council meetings. (Box 303)
      - Miscellaneous materials regarding JACL local chapters. (Box 303)
  - Japanese Associations, 23.0 linear ft.
    - Records regarding Central and Regional Japanese Associations
      - Nanka Ch Nihonjin Kai [characters] [Central Japanese Association of Southern California], Los Angeles. (Box 229-230)
        This regional Japanese Association was created with a view to coordinating the activities of and reconciling differing views among the members of local Japanese Associations which were established within the jurisdiction of the Japanese Consulate of Los Angeles (Southern California, Southern Nevada, Arizona, and New Mexico). It was founded in 1915, and began sending its delegates to the annual meetings of the Taiheiy Engan Nihonjin Kai Kygikai [Pacific Coast Japanese Associations Deliberative Council] (see Box 728), one of the central bodies affiliated with the Zaibei Nihonjin Kai [Japanese Association of America] (see Box 230), after 1917 (the 4th meeting).
        - Gijiroku [characters] [Minutes of meetings]., August 21, 1915-January 13, 1934; (1 item) (Box 229)
        - Nisshi [characters] [Daily records]. Volume 1-2., March 10, 1930-May 13, 1931; February 21, 1938-February 23, 1939; (2 items) (Box 229)
        - San'ind shinsai gienkin bosha shimei [characters] [List of contributors for the relief of the victims of the San'ind Earthquake]., 1927; (1 item) (Box 229)
        - Shimbun kirinuki-ch [characters] [Newspaper clippings]., 1922; (1 item) (Box 230)
    - The Japanese Association of America [Zaibei Nihonjin Kai (characters)], San Francisco., 0.5 linear ft.
      It was organized in January 1908 as the central organization for the Japanese residing in America. It replaced the Zaibei Nihonjin Reng Kygikai [characters] [Japanese Deliberative Council], an organ established in May 1905 in San Francisco to cope with the sudden outbreak of anti-Japanese incidents on the West Coast of the United States. The association lasted until 1941.
      - Kanjch [characters] [Account book]., January 1915-September 1920 (Box 230)
    - Aidaho-sh Nihonjin Kai Reng Kygikai [characters] [United Japanese Association of Idaho], Pocatello, Idaho., 0.5 linear ft.
      It was organized in 1913 to coordinate the activities of and exchange information among the members of local Japanese Associations in the state of Idaho. It is comparable to the Taiheiy Engan Nihonjin Kai Kygikai [Pacific Coast Japanese Associations Deliberative Council] on the West Coast.
      - Hasshinbun kbo [characters] [Records of out-going correspondence]., January 18, 1921-March 2, 1922; (3 books) (Box 254)
      - Shinsho rai hikae [characters] [Records of in-coming and out-going correspondence]., January 26-March 28, 1919; (1 book) (Box 254)
      - Kaiin meibo [characters] [Membership roster]., 1917-1920; (1 book) (Box 733)
    - The Japanese Association of Los Angeles, 9.0 linear ft.
      Initially it was organized as the Rafu Nihonjin Kyogikai [characters] [Japanese Deliberative Council of Los Angeles] in June 1905 (see Box 240). When the Zaibei Nihonjin Kai [Japanese Association of America] (see Box 230) was created in 1908, it was reorganized as one of the local associations, and renamed the Rafu Nihonjin Kai.
      - Gosokui yhaishiki shohiy kessan hkoku [characters] [Closing accounts for the occasion to celebrate the coronation of the Showa Emperor: A report]., November-December 1928; (1 book) (Box 231)
      - Hi-kaiin oyobi kazoku trokubo [characters] [Register book for nonmembers and their families]., 1916; (1 book) (Box 231)
      - Kaihi bosh iin-meibo [characters] [Roster: Members of the Membership and Fees Committee]., 1939-1940; (1 book) (Box 231)
      - Kaihi bosh seisekihy [characters] [Status report on the collection of fees from the members]., 1940; (1 book) (Box 231)
      - Kaiin meibo [characters] [Membership roster]. Vols. 1-6., 1910-1921; n.d.; (6 books) (Box 233)
        Scope and Content
        Box 233 includes membership rosters #5 and 6.
      - Kash Tochih shsei oyobi Ozawa jiken ni kansuru kifukin bosh kuiki oyobi iin hy [characters]., 1919; (1 book) (Box 235)
        [Lists showing the members of the fundraising committees for the amendment of the California Alien Land Law and in support of the Ozawa Case, and the districts selected for the fundraising efforts].
      - Kifukin [characters] [Donations]., September 21, 1934-February 2, 1937; (1 book) (Box 238)
      - Kgun imonbukuro [characters] [Gift packages for the Imperial Army of Japan]., March 19-May 27, 1940; (1 book) (Box 235)
      - Kyshi shaon bansankai kankei shorui [characters] [Documents and records regarding the annual banquets to honor teachers]. Include correspondence., 1935-1941; (7 folders) (Box 236)
      - Monthly statements. in account with the Yokohama Specie Bank, Los Angeles Branch., 1936-1941; (2 books) (Box 235)
      - Rafu Nihonjin Kai kiroku [characters] [Records of the Japanese Association of Los Angeles]., (4 books) (Box 237-238)
        vol.1, January 9, 1917-April 29, 1929
        vol.2, March 19-December 30, 1929
        vol.3, May 1, 1929-January 12, 1932
        vol.4, January 21, 1932-October 14, 1936
      - Rafu Nihonjin Kai Kaikeibo [characters] [Account books]. Vols. 1-11., January 1910-October 1941; (11 books) (Box 233-235, Box 729)
      - Rafu Nihonjin Kai Certificate Record (6 volumes) (Box 238-240)
        Vol.1 January, 1909 - January, 1911 Vol.2 September 1910 - May, 1911 Vol.3 January, 1911 - January, 1912 Vol.4 January, 1912 - March, 1913 Vol.5 January, 1914 - April, 1917 Vol.6 May, 1917 - June, 1918 Vol.7 June, 1918 - December, 1919 Vol.8 December, 1919 - December 1920
      - Rensh kantai kangei kiroku suitbo [characters] [Records on the closing accounts for the welcoming reception for the officers and crews in the Japanese Imperial Navy's Training Squadron]., July 1922; (1 book) (Box 238)
      - Shimbun kirinuki [characters] [Newspaper clippings]., 1931-1940; (5 scrapbooks) (Box 730, 733)
        Rafu Nihonjin kai Shimbun kirinuki (vol.1-vol.5)
        vol.1: 1931 vol.2: 1933 vol.3: 1934
        vol.5: 1939
      - Yachin Nesage Kisei Dmeikai kiroku [characters] [Records of the Tenant League]., June 1931-November 1937; (1 book) (Box 240)
        Also, Chhei yyosha jimu; shmei, todokede jimu [characters] [Matters regarding the filing of petitions for draft deferment and the issuance of certificates for draft deferment].
    - Taiheiyo Engan Nihonjin Kai Kygikai [characters] [Pacific Coast Japanese Associations Deliberative Council], 0.5 linear ft.
      It was organized to coordinate the activities and reconcile conflicting interests and aims of all the regional and local Japanese Associations on the West Coast, including the one which was established in British Columbia, Canada. The first meeting of the Council was convened in Portland on July 15, 1914. The last meeting (16th) was held again in Portland on July 15, 1929. The Nanka Ch Nihonjin Kai [Central Japanese Association of Southern California] (see boxes 229-230) began to send its delegates to the Council's annual meetings after the fourth meeting that was held in Los Angeles in 1917. In addition to the sixteen regular meetings, two extraordinary meetings were held: February 1920 (San Francisco) and July 1923 (Seattle).
      - Gijiroku [characters] [Minutes of meetings]., July 1914-July 1929; (1 volume) (Box 728)
        The minutes of all but one of the sixteen annual meetings that were convened between July 1914 and July 1929 are preserved.
    - Records and Documents regarding Local Japanese Associations in California, 4.0 linear ft.
      - Bkurei Nihonjin Kai [characters] [Japanese Association of Berkeley], Berkeley. (Box 231)
        - Kaikeibo [characters] [Account book]., March 1925-December 1930; (1 item) (Box 231)
      - Kawashimo Nihonjin Kai [characters] [Japanese Association of Walnut Grove], Walnut Grove. (Box 241-243, 729-730)
        It was organized in August 1908 originally as an agricultural association, Kawashimo Ngy Dmei Kai [characters] [Japanese Producers Association of Walnut Grove]. It was renamed as the Japanese Association of Walnut Grove in 1909.
        - Kiroku [characters] [Records], v.1-6., 1908-1942; (6 books) (Box 242-243, Box 731, 733)
          vol.1, August 11, 1908-March 6, 1922
          vol.2, March 15, 1922-October 8, 1923
          vol.3, January 6, 1924-February 20, 1926
          vol.4, February 25, 1926-June 3, 1930
          vol.5, June 14, 1930-April 29, 1939
          vol.6, June 1, 1939- February 7, 1942
        - Kaikeibo [characters] [Account book]., January 1913-March 1922; (1 book) (Box 732)
      - Rafu Nihonjin Kygikai [characters] [Japanese Deliberative Council of Los Angeles], Los Angeles. (Box 240)
        The precursor of the Rafu Nihonjin Kai (see Boxes 231-235 and Oversize boxes 729-730).
        - Kaiin meibo [characters] [Membership roster]., June 1905-December 1907; (1 book) (Box 240)
      - Sutanisurausu Nihonjin Kai [characters] [Japanese Association of Stanislaus County], Turlock, California. (Box 241)